A Guide to the Maria Rudzinska papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA195
Rockefeller Archive Center
Maria Rudzinska papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1952-1988
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
Rudzinska, Maria A.
FA195
1 Cubic Feet 2 boxes
2 boxes
Biographical/Historical note
Maria A. Rudzinska (1904- ), a protozoologist and professor emeritus, began her association with The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research/University in 1952. She worked as a guest investigator with William Trager in the parasitology laboratory. One of Maria Rudzinska's most significant finding was that malaria parasites feed on their host by endocytosis, engulfing large portions of the red blood cell cytoplasm into food vacuoles. She was also one of the first researchers to use electron microscopy in the study of parasitology. Rudzinska focused primarily on tokophyrya, studying its structure and physiology.
Dr. Rudzinska was born in Dalorova, Poland on January 4, 1904. She graduated from the Jagellonian University of Cracow in 1926 with an M.S. in biology and a Ph.D. in zoology in 1929. After emigrating to the U.S. in 1945, she worked as a research associate and instructor in Biology at New York University (1946-1952).
Scope and Contents note
Reprints. Incomplete set.
Arrangement note
Arranged in chronological order.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 R836
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research.
Endocytosis; Parasitology; Life sciences; Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Medical technology; Biochemistry; Medicine, Preventive; Medical research; Medical education; Medical sciences; Protozoology; Malaria; Zoology; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University; Rudzinska, Maria A.
- Reprints, 1952-1988
  - #21, 27, 31, 34, 37-41, 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - #46, 49, 54a, 56, 58, 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - #65-68, 71-75, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - #77-83, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - #84, 86-89, 91, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - #92, 99, 102-105, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - #108-112, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - #123-125, 127, 130, 132, 135-138, 1976-1977, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - #140-142, 144, 146, 147, 149-151, 154-155, 1983-1984, 1986-1988 (Box 2, Folder 2)